# MAHMUD IBRAHIM



#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Solution-driven professional excelling in highly collaborative work environment, finding solutions to challenges and focused on customer satisfaction. Proven experience developing consumer-focused web applications using HTML, CSS, PHP, JavaScript and Laravel Framework. Experience in building IoT gadgets, devices and web application, meeting highest standards for web design, user experience, best practices, scalability and speed. Responding to challenges by designing and developing solutions and building web applications aligned to customer's services. Translating solutions into code and working across many different APIs, third-party integrations and databases.

#### **WORK HISTORY**

## 1. **Project Engineer, 11/2012 to 02/2020 (7 Years)**

Centre For Energy Research, United International University, Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Performed as "Sr. Research Engineer cum Web Developer"
- Design & developed IoT gadgets and devices with hardware, firmware, software and web application.
- Designed, implemented and monitored web applications for continuous improvement.
- Used programming capabilities in *Embedded C, Python, PHP, SQL and JavaScript* and other libraries as needed.
- Developed web applications, dashboards for interactive data visualization and demonstrating M2M communication.
- Researched new technologies, software packages and hardware products for use in web application projects.
- Experience in Embedded firmware development, testing & implementation
- Project management & Co-ordination

Address: 10-C/3, Madrasa Road, Aziz Moholla, Mohammudpur, Dhaka-1207

**Phone:** 8801675306077

**Email:**embeddedworld24@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/mah mud-ibrahim-547a6069/



### **SOFT SKILLS**

- ❖ Agile workflow processes
- Web development projects
- Product Development
- Technical Support
- Problem Solving
- Project Management
- Web user interfaces

#### HARD SKILLS

- Frontend Technology
  - ✓ HTML, CSS, JavaScript
  - ✓ Bootstrap, jQuery, Ajax
- Frontend Framework
  - ✓ Vue JS
  - ✓ React JS
- ❖ Backend Technology
  - ✓ PHP
  - ✓ Python
- ❖ Backend Framework
  - ✓ Laravel
  - ✓ Django
- ❖ Database: MySQL, PostgreSQL
- ❖ Version Control: Git
- ❖ Payment Gateway & SMS Integration
- Embedded System: Microcontroller, Raspberry Pi (Linux)
- Firmware Development for MCU
- ❖ Electronics Circuit & PCB Design

Technical support, report and research proposal writing.

## 2. Adjunct Faculty, 06/2015 to 08/2018 (3 Years)

Dept. Of EEE, United International University, Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Designed and delivered class instruction to meet course competencies
- Examined and critiqued course material while including instructor-specific policies
- Developed creative and effective teaching methods for course content to capture student's attention
- Supervised more than 15 under grade Thesis/Project

#### PROJECT EXPERIENCE

## > Web Application Development

- ✓ Technology used: PHP, Vue JS, Bootstrap, Laravel, Python, Django MySQL, SSlcommerz, SMS gateway etc.
- > Demand Response Enabled Smart Grid with centralized monitoring & control integrated with mobile prepayment. (2018-2020)
  - Hardware Technology used:
     Arduino, Micro-Controller, M2M communication using IoT,
     MQTT protocol, GSM/GPRS, LoRaWAN/LPWAN
  - ✓ Software Technology used: Embedded C/C++, Python, PHP, Laravel, MYSQL, SMS & payment Gateway integration, Big Data handling and device to server communication.
- > Automatic Solar Irrigation system with remote monitoring and prepaid billing. (2015-2018)
  - Hardware Technology used:
     Arduino, Micro-Controller, M2M communication using IoT,
     MQTT protocol, GSM/GPRS, Wireless RF/Zigbee Tech,
     Solar Energy.
  - ✓ Software Technology used: Embedded C/C++, Python, PHP, Laravel, MYSQL, SMS & payment Gateway integration, Wireless Mesh networking, Big Data handling and device to server communication.
- > Remote data logging system with web application for centralized monitoring of Battery Bank. (2013-2015)
  - ✓ Hardware Technology used:
     Arduino, Micro-Controller, Wireless RF/Zigbee Tech.
  - ✓ Software Technology used: Embedded C/C++, HTML, JavaScript, PHP, MySQL.

## **AFFILIATIONS**

Institute of Engineers (IEB)
[Member: M -39360]

#### **ACHIEVEMENT**

Patent

Title: A system and method for smart irrigation system, BD-1006043, Patent#324/2016, Dept. of Patents, Designs and Trademarks, Bangladesh]

#### **COURSE & TRAINNING**

- Professional Web Development Institute: Creative IT, Dhaka, BD
- Design and Operation of Offgrid systems
   Institute: SMA Solar Academy
   (Germany) & IDCOL (JV), Dhaka,
   BD
- Circuit and Layout Design Institute: VLSI Training Academy (VTA), United International University, Dhaka, BD

# **EDUCATION**

Examinations passed	School/College/University	Performance	Year of	Specialization
		CGPA/GPA	passing	
M.Sc. in Computer	United International	4.00/4.00	2017	Embedded System,
Science and Engineering	University, Dhaka,			Internet of Things
(MSCSE)	Bangladesh			(IoT) technology,
				Web Design and
				Development
B.Sc. in Electrical and	United International	3.29/4.00	2013	Renewable Energy,
Electronic Engineering	University, Dhaka,			Electronics, Power
(BSEEE)	Bangladesh			System
H.S.C	Dhaka City College	4.50/5.00	2007	Science
S.S.C	Mohammudpur Govt	5.00/5.00	2005	Science
	High School			

# **AWARD & CERTIFICATE OF EXCELLENCE**

		T		
SN	Award/Certificate	Awarded by	Award Type/Year	Field
1	Inter University Innovation Project	Ministry of Power,	National Award,	Research,
	Award	Energy and Mineral	2018	Innovation, &
	(Power & Energy Week - 2018)	Resources,		Development
	Project Name: "Demand Response	Bangladesh		
	Enabled Smart Grid"	(MPEMR)		
2	Inter University Innovation Project	Ministry of Power,	National Award,	Research,
	Award	Energy and Mineral	<i>2016</i>	Innovation, &
	(Power & Energy Week - 2016)	Resources,		Development
	Project Name: "Automatic solar PV	Bangladesh		
	irrigation system suitable for	(MPEMR)		
	Bangladesh"			
3	Certificate of Appreciation &	Dept. of EEE, United	Appreciation	Service, support &
	contribution to student	International	certificate, 2013	contribution to
	community/club (UIUEEC)	University		academic level
				student community
4	Certificate of Excellence/Achievement	Dept. of EEE, United	1 <sup>st</sup> Place, in EEDay-	University level
	(University level project competition)	International	2012	project competition
		University		

I hereby declare that all of the information given above is true to the best of my sense and belief.

Signature:

Mahmud Ibrahim